After this battle
После этой битвы
Xuan Kingdom quickly cleared the remaining forces in the central plains
страна Сюань быстро уничтожила оставшиеся силы врага в Чжунъюане
Completed the recovery of lost territories
выполнив древнюю мечту вернуть все родные земли
The old wish to recover the divine land
и воссоединить Поднебесную
Your Majesty
Ваше Величество
These years have been hard on you
Эти годы были для тебя нелёгкими
Building the Great Wall
То Великая стена
Expeditions to the northern desert
то поход в Мобэй
Without you coordinating in the middle
Без твоей поддержки и планирования
These matters
всего этого
I couldn't accomplish
я бы не справился
This old minister
Я всего лишь
Is Your Majesty's servant
слуга Вашего Величества
To share Your Majesty's worries and solve problems
Делить с вами тяготы и устранять беды
Is what your servant
это
Should do
мой долг
Embezzlement and bribery
Взяточничество коррупция
Building factions
формирование клики
I didn't want to discuss these with you
Я не хотел говорить с тобой об этом
Your Majesty
Ваше Величество
Your servant retires
Я ухожу
This retirement is for a lifetime
И этот уход навсегда
This life
В этой жизни
This life of assisting Your Majesty
я служил Вам
Your servant
и
Has no regrets
не жалею ни о чём
The 30th year of Longwu
В тридцатом году эры Лунъу
Duke of Qingguo Xie Jian'an was impeached by the Censorate and imprisoned
герцог Цин Се Цзяньань был обвинён и заключён под стражу
Committed suicide to avoid punishment
Страшась суда он покончил с собой
All family property was confiscated
Все его имущество было конфисковано
When the people heard
а народ
They all clapped in approval
с радостью воспринял эту новость
In the ten years that followed
В течение последующих десяти лет
The realm gradually became peaceful
страна жила в мире
No more warfare
войны более не было
The 40th year of Longwu
В сороковом году эры Лунъу
Sikong Yao died of illness
Сыкун Яо скончался
Crown Prince Sikong Sheng ascended the throne
Его трон унаследовал наследный принц Сыкун Шэн
The following year, changed the era name to Yongning
На следующий год была провозглашена новая эра Юннин
Posthumously titled the late Emperor Sikong Yao as Ming
Ушедшему императору дали посмертное имя Мин
Historically known as
в истории он остался как император Сюаньмин